A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z FA394
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA394
45.2 Cubic Feet Boxes 423-535
Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable.
Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
File Plan note
RG 12
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation officers' diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential., The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
Conditions Governing Access note
Officers' diaries are open for scholarly research provided that (1) the diarist is deceased and (2) the volume to be examined is at least twenty years old. All reasonable efforts will be made to determine the fate of the diarist(s), but if such efforts are fruitless then the material will remain closed to scholarly research until 100 years after the officer's year of birth.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries include:
FA391 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries A-E.
FA392 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries F-L.
FA393 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries M-R.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by surname.
Philanthropy -- United States; Humanities; Epidemics; Medical sciences; Philanthropy; Life sciences; Race and society; Public health; African Americans; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Arts; Diseases; Charities
- Salant, Walter S.
  - 1960-1961 (Box 423)
- Sanders, Alvin Joyner
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted - RF Officer Diaries.
  - 1971-1972 (Box 423)
  - 1973 (Box 423)
- Sanders, Morris B.
  - 1931-1932 (Box 424)
- Sandt, Donald G., Jr.
  - 1968-1970 (Box 424)
- Sasse, Bruce E.
  - 1949-1954 (Box 424)
- Saxton, George A.
  - 1963-1967 (Box 424)
- Sawyer, Wilbur A.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files and user copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  Africa; South America; Asia; Australia
  - Reports, 1924-1925, 1930 (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 1)
  - Report on Ceylon Part 1, February 22, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 16 pages
    Sri Lanka; Sanitation; Public health; Hygiene; Hookworm disease
  - Report on Ceylon Part 2, March 17, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 22 pages
    Malaria; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Sri Lanka; Sanitation; Public health
  - Report on Ceylon Part 3, March 21, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 14 pages
  - Report on Trip to Madras Presidency, April 28,1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 18 pages
    Sanitation; Medicine, Preventive; Public health; India; Medical education; Hookworm disease; Hygiene
  - Report on Trip to Calcutta, Santiniketan, and Bombay, May 3, 1924; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 10 pages
    Scope and Contents note
    Brief report addressed to Dr. Victor G. Heiser, Director for the East, International Board of Health regarding local Malaria Campaigns. Sawyer interviews professionals in the field of public health, tours and surveys medical facilities and education.
    Hygiene; Sanitation; Medical education; Public health; India; Malaria
  - Report on Visit to Venezuela, June 12, 1925; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 13 pages
    Brief report addressed to Dr. F.F. Russell, General Director International Health Board regarding tropical diseases in Venezuela. Sawyer interviews professionals in the field of public health regarding Malaria, Hookworm and Sanitation in Caracas.
    Malaria; Sanitation; Public health; Venezuela; Hookworm disease
  - 1924-1928, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 414 pages (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 157)
    The diaries are arranged by interview and visit. From 1924-1926, Sawyer is the director of the International Health Board Public Health Laboratory Service. These entries concern Rockefeller Foundation laboratories, meetings with professionals in the field of public health and conferences pertaining to hookworm. In 1926, Sawyer goes on assignment to the West African Yellow Fever Commission, Lagos, Nigeria. In west Africa he documents laboratory research various field studies on the symptomology and pathology of Yellow Fever Includes "Localities infected with yellow fever in 1926" chart.
    In 1927, Sawyer becomes the associate director of Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division.
    In 1935, Sawyer becomes director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division after Fredrick F. Russell retires. This diary is organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects, research and proposals. He is involved in administrative duties of the International Health Division. This diary includes a 1935 index.
    The 1936 diary is organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects, research and proposals. He is involved in administrative duties of the International Health Division. This diary includes a 1936 index.
    Diaries; Nigeria; Medicine, Preventive; Malaria; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Ghana; Yellow fever; Vaccines; Urine -- Analysis; United States; Tropical medicine; Public health
  - Trip of Inspection of Yellow Fever Activities in Brazil, May 15, 1930; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 11 pages
    A brief report made by Sawyer regarding Yellow Fever activities in Brazil.
    Brazil; Yellow fever; Public health
  - Trip of Inspection of Yellow Fever Activities in Brazil, May 25, 1930; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 32 pages
    Public health; Brazil; Yellow fever
  - Index, 1935 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 395, Box 425)
  - 1935 (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 399)
  - Index, 1936 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 442, Box 425)
  - 1936 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 452, Box 425)
  - Index to Trip with Dr. Warren Acting Director, 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 4 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 608, Box 425)
    1937 Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
    indexes (reference sources)
  - 1937, Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 25 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 612, Box 425)
    Brief diary notes of Andrew J. Warren acting for Wilbur A. Sawyer. Arranged by interview.
    Diaries; United States; Public health
  - Index (Excluding Visit to Far East), 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 8 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 637, Box 425)
    1937 Index; 8 pages; alphabetical
  - Visit to the Far East, 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Peking. Union Medical College; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 217 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Sawyer visits the Far East and surveys the health insurance, medical education and facilities in Asia. The diary discusses the Asian RF programs.
    Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Philippines; Diaries; Public health; Medical education; Microbiology; Yellow fever; Japan; Hygiene; Malaria; Java; China; United States; Health insurance
  - Index (Excluding Visits), 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 8 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 863, Box 425)
    1938 Index; 8 pages; alphabetical
    Public health; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1937 December 8- 1938 June 30, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 1 page (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 871, Box 425)
    Front page of diary.
    Diaries; Public health
  - Index- Trip to India, Ceylon, Africa, and England, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 10 pages
    1938 Index; 10 pages; arranged by visit and interview
  - Trip to India, Ceylon, Africa and England, 8 December 1937 - 21 February 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 66 pages
    Cholera; Egypt; England; Tropical medicine; Malaria; Medical education; Nursing; Rice; France; Hygiene; India; Irrigation; Sri Lanka; Diaries
  - Index - Andrew J. Warren Acting for Wilbur A. Sawyer, 1938 January 3- June 30; Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 4 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 948, Box 425)
    Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
    Medical education; Malaria; indexes (reference sources); Tropical medicine; United States; Yellow fever; Microbiology; Nursing; Public health; Rabies
  - 1938 Andrew J Warren Acting, 1938 January 3- June 30; Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 101 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Sawyer in this 1938 diary talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Includes a letter addressed to Dr. John B. Grant from Raymond B. Fosdick.
    Public health; Rabies; Tropical medicine; United States; Malaria; Medical education; Microbiology; Nursing; Diaries; Yellow fever
  - 1938 July 1- December 30, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 1 page (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 1,055)
    1 page
    Diaries; Public health; Medical education
  - 1938 Diary Notes for July, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 44 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, these RVR notes for July through September 1938 diary talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. It includes indexes for July and September.
    Public health; Medical education
  - Index Trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 5 pages
    1938 Index; 5 pages; arranged by visit and interview
    Jamaica; Malaria; indexes (reference sources); Influenza; Public health; Tropical medicine; Microbiology; Panama; Tuberculosis; United States; Colombia; Yellow fever; Cuba; Costa Rica
  - Trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba, 1938 September 3- December 30; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 75 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer takes a trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba to survey research proposals and Rockefeller Foundation programs. He talks to professionals in the field as well as Rockefeller Foundation officers.
    Yellow fever; Colombia; Cuba; Costa Rica; Influenza; Malaria; Jamaica; Panama; Microbiology; Tropical medicine; Public health; United States; Tuberculosis; Diaries
  - Trip Index to Puerto Rico Visit, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 2 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 1)
    1939 Index; 2 pages; arranged by visit and interview
  - Trip to Puerto Rico, 1939 January 9-19; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 9 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 3)
    Sawyer surveys and tours public health facilities that help combat tuberculosis in this brief trip.
    Diaries; United States; Tuberculosis; Tropical medicine; Puerto Rico; Public health
  - Index, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 11 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 12)
    1939 Index; 11 pages; alphabetical
  - Index of Diary for Dr. Strode Acting for Dr. Sawyer, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Strode, George K.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 4 pages
    1939 Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
  - 1939 January 3-May 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 115 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 27)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research.
    Malaria; Diaries; Yellow fever; United States; Tuberculosis; Public health; Nutrition; Microbiology; Medicine, Preventive
  - 1939 May 31-December 30, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 154 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 153, Box 426)
    Medicine, Preventive; Microbiology; Nutrition; Public health; Syphilis; Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Typhus fever; United States; Venereal diseases; Yellow fever; Hygiene; Diaries; Malaria; Influenza
  - Index, 1940; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 13 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 200, Box 426)
    General note
    This frame number is unconfirmed.
    1940 Index; 10 pages; alphabetical
    indexes (reference sources); Public health
  - 1940 George K. Strode Acting, Strode, George K.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 27 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, George K. Strode acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During April 5, 1940-May 17, 1940, Strode is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    United States; Zoology; Diaries; Nutrition; Public health; Medicine; Nursing; Hygiene
  - 1940 January 2-April 4, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 79 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 317)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research. A discussion with the American Red Cross take place regarding IHD interests in Europe relating to refuges, nutrition, typhus and World War II.
    World War II; Hygiene; Nursing; Nutrition; Influenza; Malaria; Sanitation; Syphilis; Public health; Refugees; United States; Vaccines; Tropical medicine; Typhus fever
  - 1940 Index Trip to Europe, 1940 April 5- May 16; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 5 pages
    1940 Index; 5 pages; arranged by interview and visit
    indexes (reference sources); Europe; Public health
  - 1940 Trip to Europe, 1940 April 5- May 16; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); 46 pages; 47 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During April 5, 1940-May 17, 1940, Sawyer is visiting Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war.
    Diaries; Belgium; World War II; Hygiene; France; Europe; England; Refugees; Public health; Portugal; Influenza; Vaccines; Typhus fever; Spain
  - 1940 May 16-December 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 73 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 474, Box 426)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research. IHD interests in Europe relating to World War II id discussed.
    Hygiene; Influenza; Malaria; Yellow fever; World War II; Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Typhus fever; United States; Microbiology; Nursing; Nutrition; Public health; Vaccines; Diaries
  - Trip to Europe Index, 1940; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 6 pages
    France; Europe; Public health; Spain; indexes (reference sources); Portugal; United States
  - Trip to Europe, 1940 August 4- September 9; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During August 4, 1940-September 9 1940, Sawyer is visiting Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war.
    Portugal; Public health; Hygiene; Malaria; United States; Vaccines; Spain; Typhus fever; World War II; Diaries; Europe; France
  - 1940 4 August- 13 December, Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1940 August 4- December 13; Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 104 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During 4 August- 13 December 1940, Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    Diaries; Vaccines; United States; Yellow fever; Malaria; Influenza; Tropical medicine; Public health; Typhus fever; Tuberculosis
  - 1940 14-31 December Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1940 December 14- 31; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 6 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During 14-31 December 1940, Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office.
    Nutrition; United States; Public health; Yellow fever; Vaccines
  - Index, 1941; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 711, Box 426)
    1941 Index; 13 pages; alphabetical